Guide to the William F. Sollars Papers 1946-1974
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
William F. Sollars Papers
1946-1974
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections Pullman, WA 99164-5610 USA (509) 335-6691 http://www.wsulibs.wsu.edu/masc/ mascref@wsu.edu
Cage 552
Sollars,William F.
2 containers. 4 linear feet of shelf space. 102 items.
Correspondence, reports, draft essays, and administrative records concerning experimental work with the chemistry of wheat, flours, and baked products, and of involvement in professional societies.
Mr. William F. Sollars was a cereal chemist. Born on December 1, 1913, he graduated from the University of Illinois as B.S. in 1941 and from Purdue University as M.S. in 1949. From 1945 to 1947 he worked as a chemist at Northern Regional Research Lab, Peoria, Illinois. He became a research chemist at Purdue Agricultural Experiment Station in 1947 and stayed there until 1949. From 1949 to 1974 he served as a chemist in the Western Wheat Quality Labratory, Agricultural Experiment Station, Washington State University. Mr. Sollars was a devoted researcher, a prolific paper contributor and an active professional among his colleagues throughout the the United States. His academic endeavors are largely reflected in his papers. Mr. Sollars died in 1974.
The records cover the period from 1946 to 1974.
They are arranged in ten series, with all ten series contained in two cartons. Box 1 contains Series 1 and Series 2, while Box 2 contains the remainder.
While all the series are arranged according to catagories with general headings, the folders in each series are in chronological order. Series One is composed of manuscripts. Series Two deals with conferences that Sollars attended. Series Three is Reports, while Series Four holds materials under the title of Strategy. Series Five contains graphs, mostly related to experimental work. Series Six includes reprints. Series Seven consists of travel records. Series Eight is Notes, with Series Nine another sequence of Reports. The last series contains miscellaneous items. Some of the papers are undated or foldered without headings because they were found in that form and there was a lack of information that would properly identify the materials. Some three to four hundred cards containing information on hobbies and recreational activities, chiefly notes about articles in outdoor recreation magazines, were discarded from the records.
This collection is open for research use.
Records of Mr. William F. Sollars' experiences as a wheat quality lab chemist from 1945 to 1974 were donated to the Washington State University Libraries in 1982 (Accession Number MS82-15).
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Sollars, William F., 1913-1974--Archives
Baked products--Standards; Flour as food--20th century--Research--Archives
Chemists--Washington (State)--Correspondence
Agriculture; Washington (State)
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
- Series 1: Manuscripts
  - Untitled, 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Cake Flour Reconstruction, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Untitled, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Untitled, 1957-1959 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Chloride Content of Cake Flours and Flour Fractions, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Stepwise Bleaching of XSD Chloride, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Untitled, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Chloride Content of Flours and Flour Fractions, 1960-61 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Present Status of Flour Bleaching Chemistry, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Chloride Content of Cake Flours and Flour Fractions, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Present Status of Flour Bleaching Chemistry, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Data Vault, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - By Uchino and Whistler, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous Items, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Edited and approved for publication, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Revised Draft, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Soft Wheat Flour Evaluation at the Western Wheat Quality Laboratory, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Received by North Dakota State University, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Pentosans [?] of the Tailings Fraction, 1965-1967 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Untitled, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Water - Retention Properties of Wheat Flours, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Flour Fractions Effect of Varietal Diffs in Farino Absorption, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Noodle Work, [1973?] (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Flour Fractions Affecting ..., [1973?] (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Farinograph Absorption (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Statistical Data Sheet, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Data Vault, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Noodle Study, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Cole and Penic, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Revised Draft, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Series 2: Conferences
  - Chlorine Bleaching of Cake Flour Amalgamation Behavior of PWW Starches (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Pullman, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Northwest Regional A.C.S and A.I.Ch.E Meetings Seattle, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Annual Meeting, Pacific Northwest Section, American Association of Cereal Chemists, Bozeman, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - 2nd Annual Ingredient Symposium, Peoria, Ill., 1961 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Review of Manuscripts, 1963-1966 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - 47th Amnual Meeting of AACC, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - 50th Annual Meeting of AACC, Kansas & Missouri, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Manhattan, [Kan.], 1965 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Property of AACC, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - AACC-AOCS Joint Meeting, Washington-Hilton, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - 52nd Annual Meeting of AACC, Los Angeles, Cal., 1969 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - 54th Annual Meeting of AACC, Chicago, Ill., 1969 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - 55th Annual Meeting of AACC, Minneapolis, Minn., 1970 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Series 3: Reports
  - Wheat Flour Fractionation (Work at three laboratories), 1949 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Pentosans, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Viscosity, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Investigation, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Series 4: Strategy
  - Tailing subfraction, 1963-1967 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Phenol - H(2)SO(4) Method for Carbohydrates, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Series 5: Graphs
  - 1967 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 1972 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - 1973 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Series 6: Reprints
  - Soybean and Its Processings, 1941-1946 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Studies of Soybean Protein, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous Material, 1952-1964 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Viscosity Project, 1953-1959 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Interlaboratory Testing Programs, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Chlorine Bleaching Effect on Prime Starch, 1959-1962 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Chromatography of Sugar, 1960-1962 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Chlorine, 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Chlorine Bleaching Effect, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Cookie Baking Quality Project, 1962-1964 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Miscellaneous Materials, 1962-1965 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Improved Paper on Flour Bleacher, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Effect of the Subfraction of Starch Tailings on Cookie Diameter, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Redirection (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Series 7: Travel Records
  - Ohio, 1946-1949 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - St. Louis, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Northwest Regional Meeting, Portland, Ore., 1958 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Seattle, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Ohio, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Toronto, Ont., Canada, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Series 8: Notes
  - Chloride Determination by Mecury Thiocyante Displacement, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Chloride Project - Studies on Methods, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Combustion and Potentiometer, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Untitled, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Potentiometric Titration, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Chloride Results, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Chloride Ashing with K(2)CO(3) Potentiometric Petr., 1960 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Chloride Ashing with K(2)CO(3) Potentiometric Petr., 1960 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Viebork Method for Chlorine, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Chlorine Bleaching, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Cookie Flour Tailings, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Bromate Effect, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Chromatography, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - On Fraction and Reconstruction, Chloride Project, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Mechanically Kneaded Fractionations (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Gluten Sub-fractionation (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Fractionation of Water Soluables (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Series 9: Papers
- Effect of Subfractions on Starch Tailings on Cookie Diameter, 1959-1966 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - The Effect of Chlorine on Bleaching Starch, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Present Status of Flour Bleaching Industry (Box 2, Folder 49)
- Series 10: Miscellaneous Items
  - Bakery and Reconstruction, 1956-1961 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Bakery and Reconstruction, 1960-1964 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Course Instruction, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Lists of Past and Present Research Students of the Dept. of Biochemistry at Purdue University (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Photos: Farino (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Photos: Laboratory Tests (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Chlorine Bleaching Project: Strategy & Manuscript Outlines, 1957-1966 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - T. P. Project, 1962-1967 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Correspondence, 1958-1961 (Box 2, Folder 58)